Guide to the Bingham Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Hiram Bingham I, 1811-1920; Series I; 1; (2 boxes)
  - Writings of Sybil (Moseley) Bingham
    - Journal (original, typewritten and photostatic copies), 1811-1847, undated (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
    - "Select Hawaiian Phrases", 1823 July (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Writings of Elizabeth K. Bingham
    - "Journal of our Voyage to America on the ship Flora", 1840 August-September (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Journal, 1850 March-May (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Personal papers
    - Documents concerning publication of A Residence of Twenty-one Years in the Sandwich Islands, 1846-1847 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "A View of the Missionary Establishment of Hanaroorah Wouhou" by Dexter Chamberlain., 1820 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Mission house floor plan (oversize) (Folder 114)
    - Family history papers and photograph, 1855, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Diplomas (oversize) (Folder 114)
  - Printed matter
    - "A Narrative of Five Youths from the Sandwich Islands", 1816 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Names of the Members and Children Belonging to the Maternal Association of the Sandwich Islands Mission", 1854 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "A Brief Sketch of the Missionary Life of Mrs. Sybil Moseley Bingham," by Mrs. Titus (Lydia Bingham) Coan, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Hawaiian Missions Centennial programs, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Hiram Bingham II, 1831-1917; Series II; 4.5; (11 boxes)
  Correspondence, Writings of Hiram Bingham II, Writings of Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham, and Gilbertese language materials are arranged chronologically. Personal and biographical papers and Printed matter are arranged chronologically under each type of material.
  Series II, Hiram Bingham II, contains papers of Hiram Bingham II (1831-1908) and his wife, Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham (1834-1903). The first section, Correspondence, includes letters from friends, associates, and relatives, dated from 1841 to 1908. Many of the early letters were received by Minerva Clarissa Brewster before her marriage, including letters from her father, Jonathan Brewster. A large portion of the letters after 1892 are from their son, Hiram Bingham III, and much of the correspondence during 1908 relates to Bingham's efforts to publish his Gilbertese dictionary. Writings of Hiram Bingham II consists of early school notebooks (1841-1846), journals (1844-1854), sermons (1856-1878), a Bible Class record book (1874-1881), and published articles and letters (1856-1908). Writings of Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham consists of journals and diaries, (1856-1885) and a notebook of minutes of meetings (1887-1894). Gilbertese language materials contains manuscripts and printed matter written in the Gilbertese language or concerning Gilbertese publications. These include articles written by Hiram and Clara Bingham, hymns, lists of Gilbertese books, several issues of a Gilbertese periodical, and a history of the American missions work in the Gilbert Islands (1857-1917). Hiram Bingham's writings in this section include notes, the bound manuscript, and the printed edition of his Gilbertese New Testament (1885); "Outlines of a Grammar of the Gilbert Island Dialect" (1861); the manuscript, notes, and supplements for the English Gilbertese dictionary (1900); and "Gilbertese Commentary on the Acts of the Apostles" (1904). Personal and Biographical papers includes the printed sermon preached at Hiram Bingham II's ordination, with the charge to the evangelist given by Hiram Bingham I; manuscripts concerning missionary activities; articles and programs commemorating Hiram Bingham I; legal and financial papers; drawings, lithographs and photographs; and articles about Hiram and Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham. The final section, Printed matter, includes pamphlets and articles about foreign missions, devotional books, an article by Titus M. Coan, the obituary of Lydia (Bingham) Coan, sermons, programs and invitations, news clippings, maps, and advertisements.
  - Correspondence
    Selected correspondents within this series includes Leonard Bacon (1802-1881), correspondence dated from 1854; Elizabeth Kaahumanu Bingham (b. 1829), correspondence dated from 1892; Hiram Bingham I(1789-1869), correspondence dated from 1841 to 1869; Hiram Bingham III (1875-1956), correspondence dated from 1890; Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham (1834-1903), correspondence dated from 1850; Titus Coan (1801-1882), correspondence dated from 1869; Annie Olivia (Tiffany) Mitchell (1844-1937), correspondence dated from 1900; Philip Rakubo (in Box 10); and Benjamin Silliman (1816-1885), correspondence dated from 1854.
    Partial alphabetical index to correspondence can be found in box 113.
    - 1841-1859 (Box 3, Folder 1-30)
    - 1860-1891 (Box 4, Folder 31-57)
    - 1892-1900 (Box 5, Folder 58-78)
    - 1901-1908 Nov, undated (Box 6, Folder 79-100)
  - Writings of Hiram Bingham II
    - Handwriting notebooks, 1841-1844 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Music notebooks, 1841-1846 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Composition book, 1843-1844 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Sermon notebooks, 1844-1845, 1854 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Drawing book, 1845 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Private journals, 1844-1852 (Box 7, Folder 106-107)
    - Journal of trip to Europe (3 volumes), 1854 May-November (Box 7, Folder 108-109)
    - Notebook of letters sent and received, 1857-1864 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Bible class record book, 1874-1881 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Sermons, 1856-1878, undated (Box 7, Folder 112-115)
    - "The Missionary in His Relations to Literary and Manual Employment", Undated (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Published articles and letters, 1856-1908, undated (Box 7, Folder 117-119)
  - Writings of Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham
    - Journal, 1856-1874 (Box 8, Folder 120-125)
    - Diary
      - 1866 (Box 9, Folder 126)
      - 1866 (Box 9, Folder 127)
        Typewritten copy
      - 1868 (Box 9, Folder 128)
      - 1868 (Box 9, Folder 129)
      - 1869-1870 (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Journal, 1873-1874 (Box 9, Folder 131-132)
    - Diary, 1875-1885 (Box 9, Folder 133-135)
    - Notebook: minutes of meetings, 1887-1894 (Box 9, Folder 136)
  - Gilbertese language materials
    - "Anene, Aiabai Kristian" (hymns), 1860 (Box 10, Folder 137)
    - "Outlines of a Grammar of the Gilbert-Island Dialect," by Hiram Bingham II, 1861 (Box 10, Folder 138)
    - "Supplement to Hymns", 1862 (Box 10, Folder 139)
    - "Bokin Ekaretian Abaian..." (list of names of natives baptized), 1874 (Box 10, Folder 140)
    - "Taekon Tiaon Wiriamti," by Mrs. M. C. Bingham, 1874 (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - "Te Ronorono ni Mitinare," by Mrs. M. C. Bingham, 1874 (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - Philip Rakubo's journal, 1875-1876 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - "Te Boki n Reirei te Ware-Boki" (grammar book), 1876 (Box 10, Folder 144)
    - Hymns, 1880 (Box 10, Folder 145)
    - "Reireiaia Kaini Kiribati," by H. Bingham II, 1881 (Box 10, Folder 146)
    - "Account of Sales [of] Gilbert Islands Testaments and Books", 1882-1907 (Box 10, Folder 147)
    - "Te Nu Tetemanti" (New Testament, published with corrections by H. Bingham), 1885 (Box 10, Folder 148)
    - "New Testament" (bound manscript), by H. Bingham, [1885] (Box 11, Folder 149)
    - New Testament: notes and corrections, 1864, 1887 (Box 11, Folder 150)
    - New Testament: notes for translation, by Mrs. M. C. Bingham, 1892 (Box 11, Folder 151)
    - Gilbert Islands Bible: notes, 1890-1893, undated (Box 11, Folder 152)
    - "Account of Books Published in the Gilbert Islands Language", 1896 (Box 11, Folder 153)
    - Correction notes for Gilbertese publications, 1896-1908 (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - Cloth primer, 1899 (Box 12, Folder 155)
    - "English Gilbertese Dictionary," by Hiram Bingham, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 156)
    - English Gilbertese dictionary
      - Supplements, Undated (Box 12, Folder 157)
      - Notes, 1859-1871, 1902-1908, undated (Box 12, Folder 158-164)
    - Te Man n Raoi ["The Messenger of Peace"], a Gilbertese periodical, 1900-1905 (Box 12, Folder 165)
    - "A Gilbertese Commentary on the Acts of the Apostles," by Hiram Bingham, 1904 (Box 12, Folder 166)
    - Te Boki n Rei te Ware-B'ai [Gilbertese Arithmetic] by Mrs. M. C. Bingham, 1907 (Box 12, Folder 167)
    - "Te Baba n Amerika I Kiribati: A Short History of the Work of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in the Gilbert Islands, 1857-1917", Circa 1917 (Box 12, Folder 168)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts, Undated (Box 12, Folder 169)
  - Personal and biographical papers
    - Sermon preached at ordination of Hiram Bingham II, with the charge to the evangelist by Hiram Bingham I (printed), 1856 (Box 13, Folder 170)
    - Manuscripts concerning missionary activities, 1857-1908 (Box 13, Folder 171)
    - Articles and programs commemorating Hiram Bingham I, 1869-1905 (Box 13, Folder 172)
    - Legal papers, 1856-1887 (Box 13, Folder 173)
    - Financial papers, 1857-1908 (Box 13, Folder 174)
    - Scrapbook of Hiram Bingham II (oversize), 1859-1899 (Folder 114)
    - Drawings and lithographs (Box 13, Folder 175)
    - Photographs of Hiram Bingham II and Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham (Box 13, Folder 176)
      - Oversize (Folder 114)
    - Photographs, miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 177)
    - Articles about Hiram Bingham II, 1865-1915, undated (Box 13, Folder 178-180)
    - Articles about Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham, 1889-1908 (Box 13, Folder 181)
  - Printed matter
    - Devotional books, 1831, undated (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Textbook cover, 1842 (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Titus M. Coan, "The Natives of Hawaii: A Study of Polynesian Charm", 1901 (Box 13, Folder 183)
    - Obituary of Lydia (Bingham) Coan, 1915 (Box 13, Folder 183)
    - American foreign missions, 1842-1908 (Box 13, Folder 184)
    - Missionary ship, The Morning Star, 1857-1904 (Box 13, Folder 185)
    - Sermons, 1851, 1864 (Box 13, Folder 186)
    - S. J. Whitmee, "A Missionary Cruise in the South Pacific", 1871 (Box 13, Folder 187)
    - "Report of a Foreign Missionary Service", 1899 (Box 13, Folder 187)
    - Leaflets and circulars, 1842-1895 (Box 13, Folder 188)
    - Programs, calling cards and invitations, Undated (Box 13, Folder 189)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1901-1908 (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - Maps and advertisements, 1908, undated (Box 13, Folder 191)
- Hiram Bingham III, Correspondence, 1883-1960; Series III; 8; (19 boxes)
  Family correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of sender and chronologically under each name. General correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  List of Selected Correspondents
  This is a partial list of prominent correspondents in Series III of the Bingham Family Papers. For dates of letters from a particular correspondent, consult the card catalog in Box 113. Note: the catalog cards are not complete, and should not be regarded as a comprehensive index to the letters of a given individual.
  Adams, Charles Francis, 1866-
  Adams, George Burton, 1851-
  Ames, Edward Winslow
  Angell, James Rowland, 1869-
  Baker, John Frederick, 1888-1956
  Baldwin, Roger Sherman, 1869-1956
  Bartleman, Richard Milne
  Beard, Charles Austin, 1784-1948
  Beers, George Emerson, 1865-
  Boas, Franz
  Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940
  Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-
  Brandegee, Frank Bosworth, 1864-1924
  Brewster, Chauncey Bruce, 1848-
  Bryan, William Jennings, 1860
  Bryce, Elizabeth Marion (Ashton), Viscountess
  Bryce, James, Viscount, 1838-1922
  Camp, Walter, 1859-
  Canby, Henry Seidel, 1878-
  Channing, Edward, 1856-
  Chapman, Frank Michler, 1864-
  Coolidge, Archibald Cary, 1866-1928
  Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933
  Cosio, Jose Gabriel
  Cross, Wilbur Lucius, 1862-
  Dall, William Healy, 1845-
  Davis, John William, 1873-
  Day, George Parmly, 1876-
  Dixon, Roland Burrage, 1875-
  Eddy, David Brewer, 1877
  Embree, Edwin Rogers, 1883-
  Erving, William Gage, 1877-
  Farnam, Henry Walcott, 1853-
  Farrand, Max, 1869-
  Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947
  Foote, Harry Ward, 1875-
  Ford, Worthington Chauncey, 1858-
  Gallaudet, Herbert Draper, 1876-
  Garfield, James Rudolph, 1865-
  Garland, Hamlin, 1860-
  Giesecke, Alberto Anthony, 1883-
  Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-
  Gorgas, William C., 1854-
  Gregory, Herbert Ernest, 1869-
  Grosvenor, Gilbert Hovey, 1875-
  Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856
  Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-
  Hotchkiss, Henry Stuart, 1878-
  Hrdli?ka, Ale?, 1869-
  Huntington, Ellsworth, 1876
  Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-
  Jameson, John Franklin, 1859-
  Kent, William, 1864-
  Keogh, Andrew, 1869-1953
  Knox, Philander Chase, 1853-1921
  Leland, Waldo Gifford
  Lichtenstein, Walter, 1880-
  McLean, George Payne, 1857-1932
  Markham, Clements, 1830-
  Ogg, Frederic Austin, 1878-
  Peabody, Endicott, 1857-
  Peary, Robert Edwin, 1856-
  Pezet, Frederico Alfonso
  Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-
  Putnam, Frederick W., 1839-
  Putnam, Herbert, 1861-1955
  Reid, Ogden Mills, 1882-
  Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-
  Roraback, J. Henry, 1870-
  Schuchert, Charles, 1858-
  Schuyler, Livingston Rowe, 1868-
  Schuyler, Montgomery, 1843-
  Seymour, George Dudley, 1859-
  Smith, Huntington, 1857-
  Stearns, Alfred Ernest, 1871-
  Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-
  Streeter, Edward Clark, 1874-
  Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1882-
  Taft, William Howard, 1857-1930
  Tiffany, Charles Lewis, 1878-
  Vincent, John Martin, 1857-
  Wadsworth, James Wolcott, 1877-
  Whitney, Eli, 1847-
  Wilson, Thomas Woodrow, 1856-1924
  Woolsey, Theodore Salisbury, 1879-
  Series III, Hiram Bingham III, Correspondence, is organized in two sections, Family correspondence and General correspondence. Family correspondence consists of letters exchanged by members of the immediate family of Hiram Bingham III (1875-1956), including his father, Hiram Bingham II, his wife, Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham, and his seven sons. In addition, there are letters from Alfreda's parents, Alfred and Annie 0. (Tiffany) Mitchell, and her sister and brother-in-law, Charly (Mitchell) and James Jeans. General correspondence consists of all other letters received by Hiram Bingham III, including those from other relatives, such as his aunt, Lydia (Bingham) Coan. This section contains incoming and outgoing correspondence with friends, professional colleagues and associates, scholars in Latin American history and foreign affairs, political and governmental officials, and others. These letters are dated from 1883 to 1955, with the greatest number for the years 1913-1923. Correspondence related to Bingham's activities as director of the Yale Peruvian expeditions, 1911-1915, is filed with the Yale Peruvian Expedition Papers (MS 664). For a partial list of correspondents in General correspondence, see the Appendix. Dates of letters sent to Hiram Bingham are listed in the card catalog in box 113.
  - Family correspondence
    - Bingham, Alfred M. to Hiram Bingham III
      - 1908-1923 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - 1940-1956 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
    - Bingham, Alfreda (Mitchell) [Gregor] to Alfred, Brewster, Charles, Jonathan, Mitchell, and Woodbridge Bingham, 1920-1960 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Bingham, Alfreda (Mitchell) [Gregor] to Hiram Bingham III, 1906-1911, 1925, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 5-9)
    - Bingham, Alfreda (Mitchell) [Gregor] to Hiram Bingham III (typed copies), 1911 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Bingham, Brewster, Charles Tiffany, Hiram IV and Mitchell to Hiram Bingham III, 1908-1925 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Bingham, Brewster and Woodbridge to Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham, 1901, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Bingham, Hiram II to Hiram Bingham III, 1897-1908 (Box 14, Folder 13-21)
    - Bingham, Hiram II and Minverva Clarissa (Brewster) to Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham and Hiram Bingham III, 1900-1908 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Alfred M. Bingham, 1918-1932 (Box 14, Folder 23-25)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Alfred M. Bingham, 1933-1956 (Box 15, Folder 26-29)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham
      - Originals, 1900-1918 (Box 15, Folder 30-44)
      - Originals, 1920-1937 (Box 16, Folder 45-50)
      - Typed copies, 1900-1937 (Box 16, Folder 51-57)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Alfred, Brewster, Charles, Hiram IV, Jonathan, Mitchell, and Woodbridge Bingham, 1915-1945 (Box 16, Folder 58)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Brewster Bingham, 1921-1933 (Box 16, Folder 59)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Charles Tiffany Bingham, 1921 (Box 16, Folder 60)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Hiram Bingham IV, 1916-1953 (Box 16, Folder 61)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Minerva Clarissa (Brewster) Bingham, 1890 September 22 (Box 16, Folder 62)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Woodbridge Bingham, 1914-1946 (Box 17, Folder 63)
    - Bingham, Hiram III to Annie O. (Tiffany) Mitchell, 1918-1933 (Box 17, Folder 64)
    - Bingham, Woodbridge to Hiram Bingham III, 1901-1925 (Box 17, Folder 65)
    - Jeans, James and Charly (Mitchell) to Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham, 1900-1933 (Box 17, Folder 66)
    - Mitchell, Alfred and Annie O. (Tiffany) to Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham and Hiram Bingham III, 1901-1905 (Box 17, Folder 67)
    - Mitchell, Annie O. (Tiffany) to Alfred and Woodbridge Bingham, 1925-1932 (Box 17, Folder 68)
    - Mitchell, Annie O. (Tiffany) to Alfreda M. Bingham, 1909-1936, undated (Box 17, Folder 69)
    - Mitchell, Annie O. (Tiffany) to Hiram Bingham III, 1902-1935 (Box 17, Folder 70)
  - General correspondence
    - 1883-1905 (Box 17, Folder 71-79)
    - 1906-1911 (Box 18, Folder 80-92)
    - 1912-1913 April (Box 19, Folder 93-101)
    - 1913 May-September (Box 20, Folder 102-110)
    - 1913 October-1914 January (Box 21, Folder 111-120)
    - 1914 February-May (Box 22, Folder 121-131)
    - 1914 June-December (Box 23, Folder 132-146)
    - 1915 January-October (Box 24, Folder 147-160)
    - 1915 November-1916 March (Box 25, Folder 161-170)
    - 1916 April-October (Box 26, Folder 171-183)
    - 1916 November-1917 August (Box 27, Folder 184-197)
    - 1917 September-1921 October (Box 28, Folder 198-209)
    - 1921 November-1922 October (Box 29, Folder 210-222)
    - 1922 November-1923 May (Box 30, Folder 223-234)
    - 1923 June-1924 November 24 (Box 31, Folder 235-248)
    - 1924 November 25-1955, undated (Box 32, Folder 249-259)
- Hiram Bingham III, Teaching, 1893-1924; Series IV; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Section one, Harvard University, is arranged by type of material. Section two, Yale University, is arranged by type of material and chronologically under each heading.
  Series IV, Hiram Bingham III, Teaching, consists of materials relating specifically to Bingham's activities as college instructor and professor at Harvard and Yale, from about 1901 to 1916. There are no materials relating to his teaching at Princeton. These materials include lecture notes, reading lists, student examinations, course proposals, student evaluations, reports, printed matter, and background articles. Subject areas include Latin American history, South American history and geography, American colonial history, European history, and Medieval history.
  - Harvard University
    - Lecture notes
      - American colonial history (Box 33, Folder 1-9)
      - Medieval history (Box 33, Folder 10-14)
      - European history (Box 34, Folder 15-17)
    - Notes for public lecture: "History as Art or Science?" (Box 34, Folder 18)
    - Reading list and references: Medieval history (Box 34, Folder 19)
    - Report on publications relating to the Harvard Library (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - Student examinations: Medieval history (Box 34, Folder 21)
    - Seating plans, examinations and section notes: Medieval and European history (Box 34, Folder 22)
  - Yale University
    - Lecture notes
      - Early Man in America and the Incas, Undated (Box 34, Folder 23)
      - Latin American history, 1908-1910, undated (Box 34, Folder 24-25)
      - Bibliographical talk on Latin American history, 1909 (Box 34, Folder 26)
      - South American geography, Undated (Box 34, Folder 27)
      - South American history, 1909-1911 (Box 34, Folder 28-30)
      - South American history, 1913-1917 (Box 35, Folder 31-34)
      - South American history: general notes, 1909 (Box 35, Folder 35)
      - Spanish American history, Undated (Box 35, Folder 36-37)
    - Course proposals: Latin American history, 1912-1916 (Box 35, Folder 38)
    - Examinations: manuscripts and printed matter, 1907-1915 (Box 35, Folder 39)
    - Student evaluations: South American history, 1913 (Box 35, Folder 40)
    - Student examinations: Latin American history, 1913 (Box 35, Folder 41)
    - Lantern slides: printed matter and notes, 1906-1911 (Box 35, Folder 42)
    - Printed matter, 1912-1924 (Box 35, Folder 43)
      See also: folio 114
    - Background articles: South American history, 1893-1915 (Box 35, Folder 44)
    - Reports: Graduate Club Association, 1916 (Box 35, Folder 45)
- Hiram Bingham III, Latin America, 1842-1930; Series V; 11.75; (28 boxes)
  Writings of Hiram Bingham III and Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically. Pan-American conferences is arranged by type of material. Reference file is arranged alphabetically by name of country, with note cards at the end.
  Series V, Hiram Bingham III, Latin America, consists of materials relating to Bingham's scholarship in Latin American history, not including specific teaching functions and Peruvian exploration. The first section, Writings of Hiram Bingham III, consists of manuscripts, notes, and printed editions of his works, including articles on the Scots Darien colony, South American history, United States relations with Latin America, and the Monroe Doctrine. Bingham's writings represented in this section include The Journal of an Expedition across Venezuela and Colombia (1909), The Monroe Doctrine: An Obsolete Shibboleth (1913), and the manuscript of his lectures on the Scots Darien Company, delivered at Johns-Hopkins University in 1910. The second section, Scrapbooks, consists of scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, photographs, and other material concerning Panama, Brazil, Venezuela, Colombia, South America, and Latin America. Pan-American Conferences contains invitations, reports, programs, articles, and other papers concerning the Pan-American Congress, 1908-1916, and correspondence, instructions for delegates, printed matter, and clippings concerning the Pan-American Day at Yale, 1916 January 14. The final section, Reference file, consists of research notes, pamphlets, articles, newsclippings, books, bibliographies, and other reference material concerning most of the countries in Latin America. This section also includes Bingham's note cards concerning place names in Peru, the Yale Peruvian Expedition, books, index-bibliography, and a chronological index.
  - Writings
    - "Virginia Letters on the Scots Darien Colony, 1699", 1905 July (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - "Early History of the Scots Darien Colony", 1906 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - "The Possibilities of South American History and Politics as a Field for Research": reprints, 1908 February (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - The Journal of an Expedition across Venezuela and Colombia, 1906-1907, 1909
      - MS Journal (bound), 1906-1907 (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - TMs draft, Preface, Chapters 1-11, 1909 (Box 36, Folder 4-9)
      - TMs draft, Chapters 12-15, Postscript, 1909 (Box 37, Folder 10-13)
      - TMs draft, Preface, Chapters 1-15, postscripts and appendices, 1909 (Box 37, Folder 14-18)
      - Research notes (Box 37, Folder 19)
      - "Cuzco and Sacsahuaman", 1909 (Box 37, Folder 20)
      - Excerpts from "Yale Alumni Weekly", 1909 August (Box 37, Folder 21)
    - "The Scots Darien Company"
      - TMs draft, preface, chapters 1-10, 1910 (Box 37, Folder 22-25)
      - TMs draft, chapters 11-15, footnotes, bibliography, 1910 (Box 38, Folder 26-29)
      - TMs, preface, chapters 1-13, bibliography, appendices, 1910 (Box 38, Folder 30-36)